Hello and welcome back to our image and video processing class.
大家好 欢迎回到我们的图像与视频处理课程上来
In the previous video, we saw in real time, histogram equalization.
在前一个视频里 我们演示了一个实时的直方图均衡化例子
We saw how it improves the image and how we managed to get a non-uniform histogram
我们见识了它是如何提高图像质量 并成功地将一个非均衡直方图
and make it a uniform histogram. So, let's see in detail how we do that.
转换成均衡直方图的 现在让我们深入地探索这是如何实现的
I'm going to show you exactly the math behind that and you will see how simple
当我讲解过它背后的数学原理后 大家就会发现它其实如此简单
it is. You would be able to go right away and
如果大家愿意的话
program that in your own computer if you wish to do so.
应该马上就可以在自己的电脑上将其编写出来
So, let's just dive into it. So, first of all, let's just go again and
让我们深入这个问题 首先 我们再讲讲直方图
talk about histograms. Here we see a very dark image and here we
这里是一张很暗的图像
see the histogram. As we see most of the distribution of the
这里是它的直方图 我们可以看到
pixels value, of the pixel values are in the low end of the histogram, there's not
像素值多是分布在直方图低值端
a lot of bright values and we see that the histogram basically, they are, the
比较亮的值并不多 在这个直方图上我们可以看到
count of pixels there is very, very low. Here, we see the other way around, a very
这些区域的像素数量非常非常少 这里我们看到的是相反的情况
bright image and most of the count is in the high part of the histogram.
这是一张非常亮的图像 在这个直方图上 大量像素集中在高值端
So, there is not a lot of pixels with low values.
所以这里较低的像素值并不多
Here, we see kind of a great low contrast image and then we see that the pixels are
这里 是一张灰蒙蒙的对比度很低的图像 我们可以看到它的像素
actually concentrated in the middle, while here, we see an image that looks
实际上集中在中间 这是一张看起来
much nicer. These are all the same images, this looks
好很多的图像 它们都是同一张图像 这一张看起来
much nicer and we have kind of a uniform distribution.
清楚很多 其对应的分布是比较均匀的
We're occupying the whole space of pixel values, more or less uniformly, and then
用到了全部范围的像素值 几乎是均匀的
the image looks much, much nicer. So, we want to be able to learn how to go
这样这张图像看起来就清楚了许多 所以我们想要学习
from a distribution like this to a distribution like this.
如何将一个这样的分布转换成这样的分布
And again, as I say, it's a very, very simple operation, as we're going to see
如前所述 这是一个非常非常简单的操作
in just a minute. So, our goal is to draw form a given
我们等一下就能弄懂它 我们的目标是从一个给定的分布
distribution to a uniform distribution assuming that our pixel values can go
转换到一个均匀的分布 假设像素的值是从
from zero to L minus 1. For example, standard L is 256, so we can
0到L-1 例如标准的 L是256 那么像素值
go from zero dark to 255 very bright or white.
是从0 也就是黑色 到255 也就是非常亮或者白色
And we want to get a uniform distribution.
我们希望得到一个均匀的分布
So, basically, the probability or if we don't normalize the count,
所以它的概率 如果我们没有对数量归一化
but let's just think normalize is just easier,
但是方便起见 我们仅仅考虑归一化的情形
the probability is one over L minus 1. That's basically the probability of
这个概率是 1/(L-1) 这就是一个像素达到这个灰度值的概率
having a pixel achieve that gray value. So, we want to go from this to this.
我们希望从这里到这里
That's basically our goal. In order to achieve that, what we needs
这就是我们的目标 为了达成这个目标 我们需要
to find a transform that takes basically the pixel values of the original image
找到一个以原图的像素值作为输入的变换
and transforms them to pixel values of a different image.
使它们转换成另一个图像的像素值
So, having an image and you'd basically to decide, for every pixel in the image,
所以有了一张图像之后 对于图像中的每一个像素
I want to see its value and I want to transform it to exactly the same place
我要得到像素的值 之后变换成一个新的值
but with a new value. And remember, so far, we are only making
放在同样的地方 提醒大家一下 目前为止
decisions based on the pixel value. Not on the neighborhood,
我们只根据这一点的像素值来作出决定 跟它周围的像素点无关
just on the values. If the value is seven, we need to decid
只根据它自己的值 如果这个值是7 我们需要确定
what we transform seven to regardless of what are the pixel values around it.
7要转换成什么值 而不受周围像素值影响
So, we need a transform that takes us from any pixel value to a new pixel value
所以 我们需要一个变换 将任何像素值变换到一个新的像素值
in such a way that we get a uniform distribution.
从而得到一个均匀分布
There is going to be one requirement of this transform and we are going to make
对于这样的一个变换有一个要求 我们将要做出
an increase in transform and the reason is we don't want to reverse the pixel
一个递增的变换 这样做的原因是我们不想反转像素值
values. So, we want this to be a monotonic
我们希望它是一个
increasing transform. If seven goes to ten, eight should go to
单调递增的变换 如果7对应的是10 8对应的就应该至少是10
a value at least ten, may be above ten. But we don't want it to go below ten and
也可能大于10 但是我们不希望它小于10
then we actually kind of flip the content of the image and that's not the intention
否则我们就反转了图像的内容
of histogram equalization. So, we are going to have increase in
这样并非是直方图均衡化的目的 所以我们需要
functions and finding these functions is our goal.
一个递增的函数 我们的目标就是要找到这样的函数
Now, sometimes we have strictly monotonic increasing functions that every pixel
有时我们可以得到严格单调递增的函数 每一个(不同的)像素值
values goes to a different pixel value. Sometimes, we have an increasing function
都对应一个不同的像素值 有时我们会得到单调递增函数
that is monotonic that some of the pixel value might end up with the same target.
其中一些像素值有可能对应相同的像素值
And we would see that that will happen in histogram equalization.
大家会发现 我们主要用这种直方图均衡方法
In particular, when we work with these great images and its great pixel values.
尤其是当我们处理这样的离散图像和离散的像素值时
So, we are going to end up with a transform of this style and not to
我们会采用这种形式的变换 而不是这种形式的变换
transform of this style. That's basically a problem with histogram
这是计算机做离散型数据的直方图均衡化过程中存在的一个问题
equalization in this [UNKNOWN] computers, something that we must have, we cannot
有时候我们无法避免这种情况
avoid, as we're going to see in the next. So, how do we achieve this?
我们接下来就会看到 那么我们如何来达成这个目标呢？
The basic idea is very simple. We can think about an histogram as
基本思想其实很简单 我们可以把直方图看作
basically a distribution s. So, this is where you need a little bit
一个分布s 所以这里我们需要一点点
of background in probability. But don't worry because even if you don't
概率论的基础 但是如果你没有这方面的基础
have that background, I think it's going to be almost self ex, self-explanatory,
也别担心 这部分内容基本上是很浅显易懂的
what I show next. So, we have a distribution.
我接下来要讲解的是 那么我们有一个分布
The histogram is nothing else than a distribution.
直方图就是一个分布
What's the probability of a given pixel value?
那么给定像素值的概率是多少？
We have, we now want to obtain a new one. We actually have the current one.
我们现在想要得到一个新的分布 我们其实已经有了当前的分布
So basically, we have a new, a different distribution.
所以我们有了一个新的不同的分布
And remember, what we are looking is for a map from r to s.
提醒大家一下 我们要找的是一个从 r到s 的映射
We are looking for this transform. So, it turns out, this is a basic result
我们要找的是这个变换 其实概率中有一个基本的结论
of probability that if we have such a map, then the relationship between these,
如果这个映射存在 那么这两个分布之间的
to this division, is as follows. This is the relationship.
关系就是这样 这就是它们之间的关系
So, the new probability distribution is the old probability distribution times
所以这个新的概率分布就是原概率分布乘以
the absolute value of these derivative. That's a well-known result from
这个导数的绝对值 这是一个概率分布中的著名结论
probability distribution and it's what you need to understand the rest of the
大家只要知道这个就可以理解之后的推导了
derivation. So, let us assume, for a second, and I'm
所以我们先假设一下  我将要证明
going to prove you that this is the transform the we're looking for.
这个变换就是我们要找的
Let's assume for a second that this is my transform.
我们先假设这个就是我们要的变换
So, s is a transform. So, from any pixel value, I will get a
那么 s是一个变换 对于任意的一个像素值
new pixel value. And let's write it as L minus one times
我们会得到一个新的像素值 让我们把它写作 L-1 乘以
the integral from zero to r. And I'm going to explain the actual
现在的直方图 或者说现在的概率分布 从0到r的积分
interpretation of what I'm writing in a second of the current histogram or
也就是 P(w)dw
current probability distribution, P(w)dw.
我等一下就会解释我现在写的是什么意思
So, what am I doing here? I'm basically integrating the mass, the
那么我在这里做了什么呢？ 我对这一块
number of pixels that achieve a given gray value from zero to r.
也就是达到特定灰度值的像素数量 从0到r积分
And then, I'm doing this because I'm using probability functions, so I'm
接下来我要做这一步 因为我在使用概率函数
normalized between zero and one, and I want to get back gray values.
所以我把它们归一化在0到1之间 之后再变回灰度值
So, let's look again at the transform. You count, if we are in a discrete space,
让我们再看一次这个变换 我们先数一下 如果我们是在一个离散空间中
your going to count, if you want to know to which pixel value should I transform
我们就会数一下 如果我们想要知道 当 r=7时
the value r equals seven, you count how many pixels are at zero,
应该变换到哪一个像素值 我们就要数 有多少像素值为0
how many at one, at two, and three, and so on until seven and that gives you the
有多少像素值为1 有多少为2 有多少为3 这样一直到7 就会得到
transform. I have to prove to you that this is the
这个变换 我现在来向大家证明这就是
right transform to do histogram equalization.
要做直方图均衡化的正确变换
So, let us do that. In order to do that, I'm going to compute
让我们来做这个 为了证明它 我们要计算
this derivative. And the basic idea is very simple.
这个导数 它的基本思想很简单
So, we are going to actually do ds/dr. Now, we have the explicit transform here,
我们实际上要算的是ds/dr 现在这里我们有了一个明确的变换
so we can compute this derivative. It's basically d of T(r)/dr and we have
那我们就可以计算这个导数 这其实就是dT(r)/dr
here the expression, so it's the derivative according to r of this
我们还有这个式子 所以就可以写成
expression that we have here, L minus 1 times the integral from zero to
这个式子对 r 求导数 也就是 (L-1) 乘以 从0到r
r, Pr(w)dw. I apologize that the lines, that
对 Pr(w)dw 求积分 非常抱歉 这几行
rows are going one on top of the other, but I think it's very clear.
这几行都写到一起了 不过我觉得这还是非常清楚的
So, we need to compute this derivative and if you remember basic Calculus, this
现在我们需要计算这个导数 如果你还记得一些微积分的基础知识
is a constant so it will go out, okay?
这是一个常数 所以将它提出来
And then, the derivative of this integral is what's inside the integral.
然后 这个积分的导数就是积分里面的部分
So, this is equal to L minus one times and I'm going to write this here in the
所以它等于 L-1 乘以 我要把剩下的
next line, Pr(r).
写在下一行 Pr(r)
So, we obtain that the derivative of s according to r is L minus one times the
现在我们得到了 s对r 的导数 即 L-1 乘以概率函数
probability, basically, the original histogram.
也就是原来的直方图
Now, what we are going to do, I'm going to erase this in a second but
接下来我们要做的是 我等一下会把这个擦掉
what we are going to do is basically include this here and see what happens.
我们需要把这里的这些代回去 然后看看会怎样
So, I'm going to plug this in here but look what we have here, we have dr/ds and
那么我们就把这部分代入 然后看看能得到什么 这里是 dr/ds
I have here. ds/dr.
但是这里是 ds/dr
S,o we need to invert that, it would be one over this.
所以我们需要取它的倒数 这应该是 1除以这个
And I hope that you can see what's going to happen, so let's see actually what's
我希望大家已经能看出来这里会得到什么 那么我们来看看事实上
going to happen. Again, we have P,
能得到什么 现在我们有 P
the new probability that we are looking is the old probability,
我们要找的新的概率函数是这个原来的概率函数
dr/ds, absolute value. We computed dr/ds just a second ago.
乘以 dr/ds的绝对值 我们之前已经算出了 dr/ds
So, this is the Pr(r), absolute value of one over L minus 1, that was our
那这里是Pr(r) 1/(L-1) 的绝对值 这是我们用来做
normalization, Pr(r). Now, probabilities are positive and this
归一化的 Pr(r) 概率都是正值 这个也是正的
is positive, certainly positive because L is greater than one.
因为 L大于1 所以肯定是正的
So, I can get rid of the absolute value and then I see that this will basically
所以我可以将绝对值符号去掉 然后我们就可以看到
cancel with this and I've got one over L minus 1 and that's exactly what I wanted.
它可以和这个约分 这样就能得到1/(L-1) 也正是我们想要得到的结果
Exactly what I wanted is to have a uniform, a constant probability
我们想要新的图像有一个均匀的常数概率分布
distribution for my new image, okay? So, once again, I'm going to write
我将实际的变换
again what's actually the, the actual transform is,
再写一次 实际的变换 s
which is a map of r is L minus 1, the integral from zero to r of the
是一个 r的映射 就是 L-1 (乘以) 从0到r的积分
original probability distribution of function or histogram.
对 原来概率分布函数或者直方图 求积分
So, it's a very simple function. You go and you count how many pixels have
这是一个很简单的函数 我们一直不断地数有多少个像素
a value up to r and that's your transform.
是某个特定的值 直到数到r 这就是我们的变换
Very, very simple operation. It's basically a one-line code in almost
非常非常简单的操作 在几乎所有的编程语言中
any programming language. And that will achieve us histogram
这基本上就是一行代码 这代码就能为我们做
equalization. So, let's see this in action.
直方图均衡 接下来让我们看一个实例
First, let's just take a, basically, an artificial sample, where we have eight
首先 我们有这样一组人工样本 其中有
different values here. This is a counting, so we have 790 pixels
8个不同的值 这部分是数量 我们有790个像素的值是0
that have value zero. And 1,023 pixels that have value one, and
1023个像素的值是 1
so on, and we just transformed these into a probability, and because we have been
其余类似 我们把这个变换成一个概率值
working with probabilities and this is the probability that we are going to get,
因为我们之前一直在用概率 这就是我们会得到的概率
we plug that into the formula that I just showed you, and this is what we're going
我们把这些代入到我刚刚展示过的那个式子里
to get. So, first of all.
就会得到这个 首先
This is the original instagram, Pr. This is the distribution that we have.
这是原来的直方图 Pr 这是现在我们有的分布
If you plug that into the formula which I showed, this is going to be the
如果我们把这个代入到刚刚的那个式子里 就会得到
transform. Note, it's going to be monotonic.
这个变换 注意 它是一个单调函数
And we know that because we are integrating.
因为我们是在积分 所以肯定是单调的
And let me just write that again. The basic operation was to integrate from
我把它再写一遍 基本操作是 从0到r积分
zero to r. So, the more I integrate, because what I
积分得越多 由于这里这些都是正数
have in here is positive, it's clearly an increasing function.
所以很明显这是一个递增函数
I'm only adding more and more positive numbers so it has to be positive.
这只是加上了越来越多的正数 所以肯定是正的
So, it's an increasing function, and what it tells me, it tells me that zero goes
所以这是一个增函数 它说明的是 0 对应这个数
to this number. One goes to this number, and so on.
1对应这个数 其它同理
So, it becomes a very, very simple map. And this is going to be the new
所以这是一个很简单的映射 这样就得到了一个新的直方图
histogram. Now, you may wonder, it looks more
大家可能会有疑问 它看起来是更均匀了
uniform and one of the things that happens because we are working with
但是出现了这样一个情况 由于我们在处理离散的数据
discrete data, we're working with images in the computer, we're going to have to
我们是在处理计算机中的图像 我们必须要
round numbers. So, for example, the 4.2 will become
对数字取整 所以例如 4.2 将会变成 4
four. So, we end up actually with less peaks
所以我们最终得到的峰值会比这里的少
than we have here because this ones here at the end, will merge into the same
因为这里的这些数最终会合并为一个相同的整数
integer number. And that's a price we play, we pay for
为了处理离散图像 我们必须
working with this great images. We cannot represent 6.7 and 6.8, will
付出这样的代价 我们不能表示 6.7 或 6.8
both become, although the formula tells us they should go to different numbers,
它们都会变成 虽然公式上表明它们应该是不同的数字
they will both become, let's say, seven. In a similar fashion, Let me ask the
它们都将变成 比如 7 以类似的方式 我要问大家一个问题
following question which I'm going to ask you to think for a second and then
我希望大家能思考一下
respond to me. Let's just look at an histogram that has
再回答我 让我们来看看以下这个直方图
the following form. It has only two different pixel values,
它只有两个不同的像素值
these two. It doesn't matter what exactly are the
这两个 它们的具体数字并不重要
values here, but this is the original distribution, of pixel values.
但是这就是像素值的原始分布
There are only two values in the image. This is a binary image with only two
这张图像中只有两种值 它是一张只有两种不同颜色
different colors, two different pixel values.
两种不同像素值的二值图像
And I'm going to ask you what's the relationship between the map for a pixel
我要问的问题是 这个像素值和这个像素值
value here and a pixel value here? So, let's just call this A, let's just
映射后的结果之间是什么关系 让我们把这个叫做 a
call this B, and I'm asking you the relationship between T(a) and T(b).
把这个叫做 b 我要问的是 T(a) 和 T(b) 之间的关系
Are they equal? Are they different?
它们相等吗？ 它们不相等吗？
Is T(a) greater than T(b)? Is T(a) less than T(b)?
T(a) 比 T(b) 大吗？ T(a) 比 T(b) 小吗？
So, just think for a second and give me your answer and I'm going to come back
仔细想一想然后回答这个问题 我们一会回来
right away and give you the explanation for the correct answer.
讲解正确答案的解释
So, let's look at what is the correct answer.
我们来看看哪一个是正确答案
Remember, what we are doing in histogram equalization is we are integrating,
大家回想一下 我们在直方图均衡中做的是积分
okay? So, I ask you, what's the relationship
现在我的问题是 这两者的关系是
between these two, are equal, less, or greater?
相等 小于 还是大于
We know first of all that T(b) should be greater or equal, than T(a) because we
首先我们知道 T(b)应该大于或者等于T(a)
have a monotonically increase in function. But let's just look a bit more
因为这是一个单调递增函数 但是我们来进一步看一下
in detail, what happened. This actually is going to integrate the
到底会有怎样的结果 这里实际上是
whole mass up to here. So, basically its going to integrate only
要对直到这里的值做积分 所以实际上它积分的只是这一部分
this. Here, is going to integrate everything up
从这里要积分的是 到 b 之前的所有部分
to b. But there is no new mass between a and b.
但是 a和b 之间没有其它新的值
Since there is no new mass then what happens is that T(a) would equal to T(b).
因为这之间没有新的值 所以就会得到 T(a)=T(b)
And as an extra exercise, you can think about what's going to be actually to
作为一个附加的练习 大家还可以想想 实际上
transform for this one and what's going to be the transform for this particular
这个的变换是什么 这个的变换又是什么
one. And especially, you can relate it to the
这其实是和图像的平均值有关的
average in the image, just do that as an exercise on the side.
可以在课余做一下这个练习
But this is very important illustration that the basically, transform that we're
但是这是一个很好的例子 来说明 我们在寻找的这个变换
looking for, even before we have to round or quantize because we're working with
即便是在我们需要的取整或者量化之前 因为我们是在
these great images. Even before that, it's not strictly
处理离散图像 即便在那之前
monotonic, there might be more than one values that end up with the same
也不是严格单调的 也有可能存在多个数值最终会对应到
transform. You can, of course, say, we don't really
同一个变换后的值上 我们当然可以说 我们其实
care too much about that, because in the original image there were no pixels with
并不太关心这一点 因为在原始图像中并没有
initial gray value a. And that's correct but I want to show
初始灰度值为 a 的像素 那是对的 但是我举这个例子
this both to illustrate that the transform does not have to be
是想说明两点 一点是要说明变换并不一定要
monotonically, strictly monotonically increasing.
是单调 严格单调递增的
It has to be monotonically increasing but not strictly.
它必须是单调递增的 但不一定是严格的
And also to illustrate once again that all what the histogram equalization is
还有一点 要再次强调 直方图均衡所做的
doing is basically counting the number of pixels after the value that you want to
就是数出不大于你想要映射的像素值的像素个数
mark. So, I'm counting the value, the number of
所以我们要数出 不大于a 的像素的个数
pixels up to a and then the number of pixels up to b.
和不大于 b 的像素个数
So, after this exercise, let's just see few additional examples.
在这个练习之后 我们来看看几个其它的例子
We, of course, saw examples with the online demo, but let's just illustrate
我们已经在线上展示中看过一些例子了 但是我们还是再来
one more example, which I think is very useful.
多看一个例子 我觉得这个例子很有用
I'm going back to the images that we started.
我们回到最初开始的那些图像
This was dark. This is what's happening after histogram
这一张比较暗 这是经过直方图均衡化处理后的效果
equalization and the histogram looks much nicer than before.
这个直方图看起来比之前好了许多
So, let's just look at the map. This is the map.
让我们来看看它的映射 这就是它的映射
Pixels value form here can map to here, okay?
这里的像素值会被映射到这里
So, this is my r and this is my s. And look at the map.
这边是r 这边是s 来看看这个映射
The map is basically is very, it has a very, very high slope because it's trying
这个映射非常地 它的斜率非常非常大
to very fast map very dark pixels to brighter pixels.
因为它需要很快地把一些很暗的像素映射到更亮的像素上去
So, it has a very, very sharp slope. Let's look for example at this one.
所以它有着非常非常陡的斜率 让我们来看看例如这一张图像
This one was pretty good to start from. It hasn't changed a lot and actually this
这一张本身就很清楚 它并没有改变很多 这是它对应的映射
is the map. It's almost unislope, in mapping the
它的斜率几乎就是1 对应着对角线
diagonal, there's almost no changes in the pixel values.
它的像素值基本上没有什么改变
And similar interpretations for the other two maps.
其它两个映射可以用类似的方法理解
This one actually needed, needs to darken the pixels and we see that in the
这一张图片实际上需要将像素变暗 我们可以看到
corresponding map, that basically, look what happens here.
在其对应的映射上 看到发生了什么
And this one needed to stretch the pixels.
这一张则需要拉伸像素
Remember, they were in the middle, it needs to stretch them and we actually
大家回想一下 它们实际上集中在中间 我们需要把它们拉伸开
observe that here. It's stretching the pixels from the
我们可以在这里观察到这一点 它把这些像素
middle. They were all around here to start from
从中间拉伸开了 它们开始的时候集中在这里
and it's going to stretch them and we see that it actually occupies the whole range
然后我们将它们拉伸开 我们现在可以看到实际上它把这这个值域占满了
from this which was the very big, very narrow band, that it occupies the
从这个原本直方图中占据的非常窄的范围
original histogram with very low contrast is actually mapping out to the whole
从由此产生的对比度很低的效果 现在实际上映射到了
spectrum from zero to 255 and we see that in the map as well.
从0到255的整个范围 我们在映射中也可以看到这一点
And, of course, we end up with images that are very similar, regardless of
当然我们得到了一些非常相似的图像
where we started because these images actually were created from these images,
不管它们原来是怎么样 事实上我们是从同一张原始图像中
from an original, let's say, this one, just by changing the
得到这些图像的 这一张图像 仅仅改变了它的对比度
contrast. And then after we equalize them, they look much closer.
我们对它们均衡化之后 它们看起来就很接近了
And that's a technique that is used very often to make images that we're taking
这种技术常常被应用于
under different conditions look much more similar.
使不同条件下得到的图像 看起来更加相似
We equalize the histogram, at the same time, we're making the images look much
我们对直方图均衡化 同时 我们让这些图像
more similar and then we can compare between them in a, in a much more
看起来更相似 之后我们就可以更方便地比较它们
friendly fashion. So, this is basically instagram
那么 这就是直方图均衡
equalization. What we are going to do next in the next
我们接下来在下一个视频里
video is instagram transform. What happens if I don't want to equalize
要讲解的是直方图变换 如果我不希望对直方图均衡化
an histogram? I want to transform it to an histogram
那要怎么办？ 我想要把一个直方图
that I know is going to be very good for my image.
转换成为我所知的可以改善图像的直方图
We are going to see that in the next very short video that is also a very, very
我们将会在下一个很短的视频里看到这个
simple operation. Thank you.
这也是一个很简单的操作 谢谢大家 // 果壳教育无边界字幕组 | ctzsm | 冰之冷  | 小白_远游